Well, okay. We got ourselves a new
constitution and a new threebranched,
checked and balanced federal government.
Now, I reckon it's time to throw this
new government in the deep end and see
how well it can swim. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milked,
let's get to it. Okay, as I said, the
Constitution formed a brand spanking new
federal government. But what's kind of
crazy is that the Constitution itself
only filled four pages of parchment. And
in case it's not clear, given all the
complexities of a new nation emerging in
the midst of a rapidly globalizing
world, four pages is not a lot of
detail. But its brevity was one of the
Constitution's greatest strengths. And
that's because its mandates were broad
enough to allow for interpretation and
flexibility as the nation grew and face
challenges unforeseen by the framers
themselves. And oh my goodness, there
were plenty of challenges unforeseen by
the framers. And so what we're going to
do in this video is consider those
challenges and see how those in power
responded by creating constitutional
institutions and precedents capable of
keeping the shiny ship of state cruising
through the murky waters of the early
republic. Oh, and by the way, if you
want note guys to follow along with this
video and all my videos, then check that
link in the description. Okay, first
we'll consider precedents set by the
executive branch, which is to say the
president. Now, the first president of
the United States was our boy George
Washington of revolutionary warfare. He
was chosen unanimously by the electoral
college. And as it turns out, he is the
one and only president in all of US
history to be unanimously elected.
>> You go, George Washington.
>> And look, so much of what we take for
granted about the presidency today began
with Washington. And I'm just going to
mention two of them. First, Washington
created a cabinet of adviserss. Now,
remember what I said a minute ago,
namely that the Constitution is pretty
vague on a lot of issues, and that is
certainly true of the executive. Yes,
the Constitution is specific about
certain executive powers, like for
example, that the president is the
commander-in-chief of the armed forces.
But for the most part, it just says that
the president is responsible for
executing the laws passed by Congress.
And so, in order to better discharge his
duties and organize the operations of
the executive department, Washington
created four departments: State, War,
Treasury, and Justice. And these were
headed by men who would serve as his
cabinet of adviserss. He appointed
Thomas Jefferson as Secretary of State,
then Henry Knox as Secretary of War,
Alexander Hamilton as the Secretary of
the Treasury, and Edmund Randolph as the
attorney general to lead the Department
of Justice. Now, to be clear, the
Constitution doesn't exactly mandate the
creation of executive departments. But
Washington perceived that creating these
departments would help him facilitate
the constitutional duties that are
explicitly mentioned. However, it's
going to be important to remember that
while Washington appointed these four
men to their positions, they were each
subject to Senate approval, which
demonstrates the principle of checks and
balances. And I'm not just flapping my
mouth hole about all this for poops and
giggles. No, the creation of these
executive departments highlights the
flexible nature of the Constitution as
well as the distribution of power among
the three branches. Anyway, these four
men became Washington's cabinet of
advisers, and because they were experts
in their respective fields, they were
able to help Washington make
consequential decisions. And that
precedent of a presidential cabinet has
been repeated in every presidency since.
Okay. Second, Washington created the
president of a two-term limit in the
executive office. You see, the
Constitution has plenty to say about how
the president will get elected and what
kinds of powers the president has, but
it says precisely bumpus about how many
four-year terms are allowable. And so,
in an astonishing relinquishment of
power, Washington decided to step down
voluntarily after serving for 8 years.
And that president was kept by every
president after Washington until 1940
when Franklin Roosevelt was elected to a
third term. And so it wasn't long after
that that we got the 22nd amendment
which officially limited the executive
to two terms. Now when he resigned his
post, Washington gave a farewell address
in which he called for national unity
and warned against two realities that
threatened such unity. First, he warned
against entangling foreign alliances.
And here he urged the next generation of
Americans and the politicians who would
represent them to resist the urge to
join alliances with foreign powers that
would unnecessarily drag the United
States into war or negatively influenced
the new American government. And that
warning served as one of the pillars of
American isolationism for a long time.
And then second, Washington warned
against the destructive effects of
political parties and sectionalism,
which he argued would the
republic because people might be too
devoted to divisive causes or beliefs.
And it was at that precise moment that
Jefferson and Hamilton participated in
world history's first awkward turtle.
And more on that in a moment. Okay. Now,
the second big category of change in the
New Republic was the creation of a new
institution, namely the federal
judiciary, or if you're sassy, the court
system. Now, if you read the
Constitution, you will no doubt notice
that the judicial branch received the
least amount of attention from the
framers. But Congress remedied that
quick, fast, and in a hurry by passing
the Judiciary Act of 1789, which created
a three- tiered federal court system. On
the bottom of the hierarchy was a series
of 13 district courts spread throughout
the state. In the middle, there were
three federal courts of appeals. And
then the most muscular court of all was
the Supreme Court, which held final
authority on constitutional matters and
was made up of six justices. And though
minor changes will be made to the system
over time, most of its structure has
endured since its creation in 1789.
Okay, now let's revisit the Hamiltonian
Jeffersonian awkward turtle performed at
Washington's farewell speech. You see,
the reason that turtle was so dang
awkward is because these two men, maybe
more than anyone else, were actually
responsible for the acrimonious division
that ended up creating the first
political parties in America. And by the
way, point of clarity, if you see
documents from this era, they're
probably not going to use the word
parties, but you'll probably see them
referred to as factions. So, you know,
don't get confused. Anyway, again, the
Constitution says precisely nothing
either for or against political parties,
nor does it even acknowledge their
potential to play a role in American
politics. And that's because the framers
of the Constitution believe that
political parties were at best unhealthy
for a Republican government and at worst
a clogged toilet in the whole of this
new ship of state, which if not plunged,
was about to get uh real stank. But
look, it probably shouldn't have
surprised any of them that parties were
going to form because during the
ratification debates, if you'll recall,
two distinct groups lined up on opposite
sides of the argument. The Federalists
and the Anti-Federalists. And to be
generous, we can acknowledge that both
groups basically wanted the same thing,
to avoid tyranny and preserve liberty.
But each group had wildly different
opinions about how those ends were to be
achieved. And so, as the new federal
government was in its toddlerhood, those
old factions came to life again as a
result of various issues that confronted
the new nation. Now, the first party was
known as the Federalist, and they were
basically the same group that made up
the Federalist during the ratification
debate. And to be overly general about
it, Federalists essentially favored more
federal power than state power. Now, the
poster boy for the Federalist was
Alexander Hamilton, who, as you may or
may not know, was like his country,
young, scrappy, and hungry.
Sorry. Anyway, the opposing party was
known as the Democratic Republicans, and
their ideology roughly aligned with the
anti-federalists. And again, to be
overly general, the Democratic
Republicans favored more state power
than federal power. And the poster boy
for this party was none other than
Thomas Jefferson. Okay, so if the
founders of the nation were wary of
political parties, then why in the fresh
heck did these parties form like 5
minutes after the ship of state left the
dock? Well, there are a lot of reasons,
but I'm going to tell you about four
major categories of disagreements they
had, all of which created the occasion
for the formation of rival parties.
First, the two factions disagreed over
economic policy. And the great grand
papy of contentious domestic economic
policies during this era was the
formation of a national bank. Now, as
the secretary of the treasury, one of
Hamilton's main agenda items was to
strengthen the national economy of the
United States. To that end, he proposed
the creation of a national bank, which
would solve a major economic problem,
namely the nation's credit. So, Hamilton
proposed that the federal government
assume all the states debts that they
had incurred during the Revolutionary
War. Now, I'm sure that sounds like a
pretty good deal for all the states, and
yeah, some states were altogether down
with this plan since it cleared them of
all their debt. But a handful of states,
like for example, Virginia, had already
paid their war debts, and that made such
a plan repugnant in their debt-free
nostrils. Now, I don't want to get too
far into these particular weeds, but
what you need to remember about this
plan is that by assuming the state's
debts, Hamilton predicted that creditors
from around the world would feel safer
loaning the United States money. And as
it turns out, he was right about that.
Now, the Democratic Republicans, many of
which were of prominent Virginia stock,
altogether rejected the idea of creating
a national bank. By their reckoning, to
do so was nothing more than a power grab
for the federal government against the
interests of common farmers. And their
main argument was that the Constitution
nowhere gave power to the federal
government to create a national bank.
But Hamilton went ahead and slapped back
by arguing that the necessary and proper
clause, also known as the elastic clause
in article one, did grant the authority
since collecting tax revenue presupposed
having a bank in which to deposit it.
And ultimately, the bank was created and
it led to the flourishing of the United
States economy. Okay. Now, the second
major disagreement that led to the
formation of political parties was a
debate about the balance between liberty
and order. And the big event that
illustrates this tension was the whiskey
rebellion. So at Hamilton's urging,
Congress imposed a tax on whiskey which
put serious economic strain on western
farmers who relied on the manufacturer
and sale of that beverage. Now this tax
was part of Hamilton's financial plan
which was basically an effort to raise
revenue to pay off federal bonds. But
the Democratic Republicans viewed this
tax as federalist protection of urban
industry at the expense of poor farmers.
And obviously Hamilton did not agree.
But the division was about to get real
bitter. So in 1792 farmers in western
Pennsylvania erupted in protest against
this tax. They marched on courouses and
assaulted tax collectors. And by 1794,
the rebellion grew more intense on
account of the lack of response from the
federal government to address their
grievances. Now, Washington worried that
this rebellion might spread, especially
because the British and Spanish were
eager to promote conflict between
Americans and American Indians in the
Western Territory. Therefore, Washington
went into boss mode and federalized
militias from several states to meet the
rebels with force and ultimately
suppress the conflict. Now, compared to
the federal response to Sha's rebellion
under the Articles of Confederation,
which was precisely bubkiss,
Washington's forceful actions had two
opposing effects. First, it demonstrated
that the new federal government was far
more capable than the government under
the articles to keep order in the
nation. Second, it enraged the
Democratic Republicans who felt that the
show of force against legitimate
rebellion amounted to tyranny. Okay.
Now, the third major debate that led to
the formation of political parties
concerned foreign policy. And the first
up was the French Revolution. So, the
Democratic Republicans believed the US
ought to come to the aid of the French
Revolutionaries since they had come to
the aid of the American revolutionaries.
But the Federalists worried that by
getting involved in the French conflict,
which had by now expanded to include
wars with Great Britain and Prussia and
Austria, that US trade prospects would
be harmed. Not to mention that the
Federalists believe that the revolution
had spun wildly out of control, what
with the French beheading their king and
any others who disagreed with the cause.
And again, on this count, Federalists
won the day. To that end, Washington
issued a neutrality proclamation which
kept the US out of the conflict while
simultaneously protecting American trade
interests in Europe. And that not
surprisingly enraged the Democratic
Republicans and caused Jefferson to
resign his cabinet position in protest.
And then the second foreign policy
debate between these two parties came in
the form of the J treaty. So in response
to Washington's neutrality proclamation,
France's American ambassador Edmund Jane
traveled around the country appealing
directly to American citizens to support
the French war against Great Britain.
And perhaps with the distance of
centuries, you're not feeling the full
weight of citizen Janae's actions. like
the stinking president of the United
States issued a proclamation stating
that the US would offer no aid to the
French and Jana was like, "Well, that's
dumb. I reckon I'll just travel around
your country and ask people directly to
give me money to support France."
Citizen Jane, more like citizen, you
must be outside your mind, son. Anyway,
Democratic Republicans turned up to
Jana's speeches in droves and were more
than happy to support the cause. And
Jana was actually successful in raising
a militia in America and started
capturing British ships. And not
surprisingly, that enraged the
Washington administration since it very
directly violated the Neutrality Act.
And it also got the British real saucy
on account of, well, it violated the
Neutrality Act. And so, the British went
ahead and responded by supplying arms to
American Indians in the Ohio River
Valley and encouraged them to attack US
settlements. Therefore, Washington sent
John J, the chief justice of the Supreme
Court to Britain to resolve this tension
along with several other outstanding
issues related to the peace of Paris.
Now, ultimately the J treat Treaty
gained some trading concessions with the
British, but it failed to resolve the
most pressing issues between the United
States and Great Britain. And so, the
Democratic Republicans heavily
criticized this treaty and the issues
left unsolved would ultimately lead to
another war with Great Britain, the War
of 1812. And then finally, political
parties formed in response to the debate
over the proper relationship between
federal and state governments. And to
illustrate this spicy development, let
me tell you about the Alien and Sedition
Act. Now, after Washington stepped down
from his presidency, the vice president,
John Adams, was elected. And it was
Adams who led the charge on the passage
of these laws. So the Alien Act allowed
the president to imprison and deport
immigrants without citizenship if they
were found criticizing the government's
pro- British policies. And then the
Sedition Act basically made it illegal
to criticize the government. And taken
together, these policies made it
possible for the Adams administration to
use federal power to silence disscent.
Now, as awful as that sounds, you have
to remember that whole citizen Jane
affair and how he unilaterally defied
the federal government and started
recruiting Americans to go fight with
France. So, the Alien Acts were a
response to that very real threat of
French subversion. And in the case of
the Sedition Acts, Adams and his ilk
believed that sedicious or subversive
speech made society less secure and less
free. And so, both of these policies,
whatever else you may think about them,
were just another manifestation of the
debates about what the American
Revolution meant. But to put it mildly,
the Democratic Republicans did not
approve on account of they viewed these
policies as evidence of massive federal
overreach and an infringement on the
liberties enshrined in the Bill of
Rights. And so state legislators with
Democratic Republican sensibilities
responded by passing the Virginia and
Kentucky resolution. And essentially
these resolutions stated that the Alien
and Sedition Acts were unconstitutional
and therefore uninforceable. And they
went even further to say that any
federal law that enables the government
to operate beyond its constitutional
power must be considered null and void
by the states. And we're going to return
to that little nullification nugget when
we get to the Civil War. But for now,
I'll leave it there. Okay. You can click
here to watch my other unit 3 videos or
you can click here to grab my video note
guides which is going to help you cram
all the contents of this course firmly
into your brain fold. I'm glad you came
around and I'll catch you on the
flipflop.